Andrew Dasburg and Grace Mott Johnson
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
- Grace Mott Johnson Papers, 1833-1963, Series 2:; (Box 7-10; 2.8 linear feet)
  - Correspondence, 1854, 1882-1963, 2.2:
    - General Correspondence, Unidentified, circa 1900-1954 (Box 8, Folder 35)
    - Frances H. Johnson Correspondence, 1887-1909, (3 folders) (Box 8, Folder 36-38)
    - Frances H. Johnson Correspondence, 1910-1919, 1930, (3 folders) (Box 9 (hol), Folder 1-3)
    - Ebenezer Alfred Johnson Letter, 1854 (Box 9 (hol), Folder 4)
  - Writings, 1848-1950, 2.3:
    Found here are writings by Grace Mott Johnson and others. Writings by Johnson include two brief autobiographical writings describing her early life, such as living on a farm, her interest in art, and her art education. Also found is a diary giving an account of her daily activities for one week in 1904, various handwritten recipes and menus, and several issues of "The Johnson Monthly" a home-made magazine written by Grace and her siblings and illustrated by Grace. Of particular interest is a writing entitled "Two Weeks in New Mexico," Johnson's detailed account of her stay in a cottage belonging to Mabel Dodge Luhan in Taos, New Mexico, their attempt to attend an Indian dance, and her interaction with Andrew Dasburg while there. Additional miscellaneous writings by Johnson include poems, writings about civil rights, loose diary-style writings in which she expresses her thoughts on her early life and experiences with psychoanalysis, notes, lists, and other writing fragments, some of which may be draft letters. Writings by others include a draft of an address on natural history given by her relative John Van Cleve, poetry by others, and an essay "Shall Women Vote?" by an unidentified author. Items are arranged chronologically within each folder.
    - Writings by Grace Mott Johnson (Box 9 (hol))
      - Autobiographical Writings, 1913, 1947 (Box 9 (hol), Folder 5)
      - Diary, March 27-April 2, 1904 (Box 9 (hol), Folder 6)
      - "The Johnson Monthly," June 1899-May 1903, (4 folders) (Box 9 (hol), Folder 7-10)
      - "Two Weeks in New Mexico," 1921 (Box 9 (hol), Folder 11)
      - Recipes and Menus, circa 1910s, 1919 (Box 9 (hol), Folder 12)
      - Miscellaneous Writings, 1896-1940, 1947, (3 folders) (Box 10 (hol), Folder 1-3)
    - Writings by Others (Box 10 (hol))
      - Dr. John Van Cleve, Address to His Colleagues, circa mid-1800s, (Not scanned) (Box 10 (hol), Folder 4)
      - Miscellaneous Writings, 1848-1950 (Box 10 (hol), Folder 5)
  - Financial Material, 1911-1952, 2.4:
    A small amount of financial material includes receipts for the delivery or casting of Johnson's sculptures and for the purchase of art supplies. Miscellaneous financial records primarily include account statements. Items are arranged chronologically within each folder.
    - Receipts, 1911-1914 (Box 10 (hol), Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous Financial Records, 1924-1952, (Not scanned) (Box 10 (hol), Folder 7)
  - Printed Material, 1882, 1917-1950, 2.5:
    Printed material includes a booklet containing essays on religion, an announcement for the exhibition of Johnson's artwork, and various news clippings of articles on the exhibition of her artwork and her civil rights activities. Miscellaneous printed material includes clippings of published poems and song lyrics by others and two Ringling Bros. Circus route schedules. Items are arranged chronologically within each folder.
    - Booklet, A Word: He That Has Ears, Let Him Hear, 1882, (Not scanned) (Box 10 (hol), Folder 8)
    - Exhibition Announcement, 1935 (Box 10 (hol), Folder 9)
    - News Clippings, 1935-1950 (Box 10 (hol), Folder 10)
    - News Clippings, Undated, circa 1935-1950 (Box 10 (hol), Folder 11)
    - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1917-1936 (Box 10 (hol), Folder 12)
  - Photographs, 1880s-1940, 2.6:
    Found here are photographs of Grace Mott Johnson, her family, friends, and artwork. Photographs of Johnson include a portrait of her as a small child and portraits of her as a young woman, as well as photographs of her in Yonkers, New York, on Monhegan Island in Maine, and in Taos, New Mexico. Also found are nude photographs of Johnson at the beach and bathing in a river, and photographs of her with her son Alfred. Photographs of Johnson with friends include a tintype of her with the artists Jo Davidson and Florence Lucius, another photograph of her with Lucius, with her friend and fellow artist Lila Wheelock Howard, with fellow artists Edward McCartan, Walter Frankl, and Carl Illava, and dining with various friends including the artist Henry Lee McFee. Also found here are a few photographs of other friends and family, and photographs of her artwork. Additional photographs of Johnson with Andrew Dasburg and others are found in Dasburg's papers, Series 1.5. Photographs are arranged by subject and chronologically within each folder.
    - Photographs of Grace Mott Johnson, 1880s-1924 (Box 10 (hol), Folder 13)
    - Nude Photographs of Grace Mott Johnson, circa 1910s (Box 10 (hol), Folder 14)
    - Photographs of Grace Mott Johnson with Alfred Dasburg, circa 1911-1921 (Box 10 (hol), Folder 15)
    - Photographs of Grace Mott Johnson with Friends, circa 1908-1910s (Box 10 (hol), Folder 16)
    - Photographs of Friends and Family, 1922, 1932-1933 (Box 10 (hol), Folder 17)
    - Photographs of Artwork by Grace Mott Johnson, circa 1910-1940 (Box 10 (hol), Folder 18)
  - Artwork, circa 1890-1928, Subseries 2.7:
    This subseries contains artwork by Grace Mott Johnson, including loose drawings and two sketchbooks. Loose drawings include pen and ink drawings of horses and illustrations of animals and landscapes in pencil and charcoal for "The Johnson Monthly," a home-made magazine created by Johnson and her siblings. The sketchbook dating from circa 1901 to 1902 contains charcoal and pencil drawings of animals, landscapes, and other designs. The sketchbook from circa 1911 includes two pencil sketches of her son Alfred Van Cleve Dasburg, as well as drawings of animals and preliminary sketches for her sculptures. Items are arranged chronologically within each folder.
    - Drawings, circa 1890, 1902-1903, 1927-1928, (2 folders) (Box 10 (hol), Folder 19-20)
    - Sketchbook, circa 1901-1902 (Box 10 (hol), Folder 21)
    - Sketchbook, circa 1911 (Box 10 (hol), Folder 22)